<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://utndatasystems.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://utndatasystems.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-08T17:15:03+00:00</updated><id>https://utndatasystems.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Data Systems Lab</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Launching Our Blog And Wrapping Up 2025</title><link href="https://utndatasystems.github.io/blog/2025/recap/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Launching Our Blog And Wrapping Up 2025"/><published>2025-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://utndatasystems.github.io/blog/2025/recap</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://utndatasystems.github.io/blog/2025/recap/"><![CDATA[<p>I’m super excited to launch our blog! We’ll use this space to share what’s happening in our lab, from research papers and systems to the day-to-day life of our team. To kick things off, let’s look back at 2025.</p> <h2 id="award-winning-research">Award-Winning Research</h2> <p>We were super happy to see our work recognized by the community this year!</p> <ul> <li><strong>SIGMOD 2025 Honorable Mention</strong>: Our paper <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2409.08013">“DPconv: Super-Polynomially Faster Join Ordering”</a> by Mihail Stoian and Andreas Kipf received an Honorable Mention at SIGMOD 2025 in Berlin.</li> <li><strong>EDBT 2025 Best Demo Award</strong>: We were also thrilled to pick up a <strong>Best Demo Award</strong> at EDBT 2025 in Barcelona for <a href="https://utndatasystems.github.io/virtual/">“Virtual: Compressing Data Lake Files”</a>.</li> </ul> <h2 id="collaborations">Collaborations</h2> <p>Research in data systems doesn’t happen in an ivory tower. We love working closely with industry leaders and top academic labs to solve real-world problems.</p> <ul> <li><strong>SIGMOD 2025 Industrial</strong>: We presented <a href="https://snowflakepruning.github.io/">“Pruning in Snowflake: Working Smarter, Not Harder”</a> in collaboration with Snowflake, where we explored some cool new pruning techniques.</li> <li><strong>Google BigQuery &amp; SemBench</strong>: Our work on <a href="https://sembench.ngrok.io/"><strong>SemBench</strong></a>, a benchmark for semantic query processing engines, is a huge team effort with Google BigQuery, Cornell, TU Berlin, University of Michigan, MIT CSAIL, and Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam.</li> </ul> <h2 id="a-benchmark-heavy-year">A Benchmark-Heavy Year</h2> <p>Benchmarks are the foundation of systems research. While we’ve been involved in benchmarking for a while (you might know our past work on <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1809.00677"><strong>JOB-light</strong></a>, <a href="https://github.com/learnedsystems/SOSD"><strong>SOSD</strong></a>, and <a href="https://github.com/amazon-science/redset"><strong>Redset</strong></a>), we’ve ramped up our efforts in 2025:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2506.12488"><strong>Redbench</strong></a>: We presented it at aiDM 2025, and we’re continuing to develop this workload synthesis work in collaboration with <strong>TU Darmstadt</strong>.</li> <li><a href="http://sembench.org/"><strong>SemBench</strong></a>: Our new benchmark, designed specifically for evaluating semantic SQL operators.</li> </ul> <h2 id="community-building-and-interdisciplinary-research">Community Building and Interdisciplinary Research</h2> <p>Beyond the core research, we’ve been connecting with the broader community:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Bavarian Database Day</strong>: We’re proud to have organized the very first <a href="https://databaseday.de/"><strong>Bavarian Database Day</strong></a>, which brought together researchers and practitioners from Bavaria and beyond.</li> <li><strong>Podcast Feature</strong>: Mihail Stoian hopped on the <strong>Disseminate podcast</strong> to talk about our work on robust query execution in the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HfZuVtY5lZg"><strong>episode on Parachute</strong></a>.</li> <li><strong>UTN Internal Milestone</strong>: We even published a first <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10391"><strong>cross-department workshop paper</strong></a>, which was a big step for interdisciplinary research here at UTN.</li> </ul> <h2 id="everything-else">Everything Else!</h2> <p>It wouldn’t be a proper recap without mentioning all the other cool stuff we did:</p> <ul> <li><strong>BTW 2025</strong>: I was co-organizing the <a href="https://luthramanisha.github.io/ML4Sys-and-Sys4ML/"><strong>ML4Sys and Sys4ML workshop</strong></a> at BTW 2025, and I also gave a talk about <a href="https://itu-dasyalab.github.io/btw2025workshop/">“Workload-Driven Indexing in the Cloud”</a>.</li> <li><strong>Dagstuhl Seminar</strong>: I attended a very cool Dagstuhl seminar on <a href="https://www.dagstuhl.de/seminars/seminar-calendar/seminar-details/25182"><strong>Table Representation Learning</strong></a>, which is actually where we first kicked off our work on SemBench.</li> <li><strong>Lab Offsite</strong>: We had a nice summer offsite south of Nuremberg. Between working on <strong>ML-based data compression</strong>, we managed to squeeze in some fun swimming and wakeboarding at the nearby lake.</li> <li><strong>VLDB Presentations</strong>: We were also busy in London at VLDB. We presented <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10391">“Instance-Optimized String Fingerprints”</a> at AIDB and <a href="https://www.arxiv.org/pdf/2506.13670"><strong>Parachute</strong></a> at the main Research Track.</li> <li><strong>Long Night of Sciences</strong>: We presented our agentic data analytics platform <a href="https://utndatasystems.github.io/data-loom/"><strong>DataLoom</strong></a> and our data lake file format <a href="https://utndatasystems.github.io/virtual/"><strong>Virtual</strong></a> at the <a href="https://nacht-der-wissenschaften.de/"><strong>Long Night of Sciences</strong></a>.</li> </ul> <p>All in all, it’s been a crazy year, and I couldn’t be more proud of what we’ve achieved. I’m super excited for what 2026 has in store. Stay tuned!</p>]]></content><author><name>&lt;a href=&quot;https://scholar.google.de/citations?user=y3IdRusAAAAJ&amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;Andreas Kipf&lt;/a&gt;</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I'm super excited to launch our blog! We'll use this space to share what's happening in our lab, from research papers and systems to the day-to-day life of our team. To kick things off, let's look back at 2025.]]></summary></entry></feed>